Inventory of the James C. Miller papers
Hoover Institution Archives
James C. Miller papers
1971-1989
1981-1989
89059
Hoover Institution Archives
177 manuscript boxes (73.8 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, correspondence, memoranda, notes, reports, studies, statistics, clippings, and other printed matter relating to domestic policy in the United States during the presidential administration of Ronald Reagan, and especially to policy regarding regulation of commerce, planning and implementation of the federal budget, and administration of federal government agencies.
Miller, James Clifford.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1989.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
James C. Miller III is an American economist, former US government official, and Hoover Institution senior fellow. He has held numerous government positions throughout his career, including chairman of the Federal Trade Commission (1981-1985) and director of the Office of Management and Budget (1985-1988). In 1981, Miller was administrator for the Office of Information and Regulatory Affairs and executive director for Vice President George H.W. Bush's Presidential Task Force on Regulatory Relief. Between 1977 and 1981, he was a resident scholar at the Center for the Study of Government Regulation at the American Enterprise Institute, serving as co-director of the center from 1978 to 1981.
Scope and Content of Collection
The James C. Miller papers consist primarily of speeches and transcripts relating to domestic policy in the United States during the presidential administration of Ronald Reagan. Writings, memoranda, correspondence, notes, reports, studies, photographs, and printed matter are also included. The collection spans the years 1971 through 1989, with the bulk of the material covering the period from 1981 to 1988. Subjects include regulation of commerce, planning and implementation of the federal budget, and administration of federal government agencies.
Arrangement Statement
Descriptions of contents reflect the majority of items in each box. Please note that not all items or subjects in a container may be listed.
United States--Politics and government--1981-1989.; United States--Commerce.; Trade regulation--United States.; Budget--United States.; United States. Federal Trade Commission.; United States. Office of Management and Budget.; Reagan, Ronald.
- Federal Trade Commission (FTC) material, 1981-1989 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes major policy statements, official reports, notes, and memoranda from speaking engagements.
- Fiscal years 1987-1989 budget material, 1983-1989 (Boxes 1-3)
  Material for this file, and all subsequent fiscal year budget material files, includes congressional budget reviews, administration material for government agencies, reports, memoranda, and press material related to the Office of Management and Budget (OMB's) administration or proposed administration of the federal budget for the described fiscal year.
- Clippings (biographical), 1983 (Box 2)
  Contains clippings of news and magazine articles either quoting or referring to Miller. Also includes a series of folders titled "The Miller File" with collected notes, memoranda, correspondence, articles, and reports.
  See also: Boxes 15, 38, 47-48, 149-151, 175-176.
- Transcripts of FTC confirmation hearings, 1985-1989 (Box 3)
- Congressional testimony, 1981-1983 (Box 3)
  Includes notes and transcripts of statements made by Miller before various congressional committees. Subjects and material relate to both the FTC and the OMB.
  See also: Boxes 31-34, 75-77, 124, 129-132, 152-153, 166-171, 174.
- Council on Wage and Price Stability subject file, 1976-1977 (Box 4)
  Includes notes and memoranda.
- Fiscal year 1987 budget material, 1986-1987 (Box 4)
- Speeches, 1983-1984 (Boxes 4-9)
  Includes notes, drafts, and related travel material. Subjects relate to both the FTC and the OMB.
  See also: Boxes 12-13, 16-21, 24, 85, 87-89, 107-108, 116, 129-132, 146-148, 156-166, 177.
- Printed matter, 1981-1985 (Boxes 10-11)
  Contains copies of the Congressional Record from 1981-1985.
- Fiscal year 1988 budget material, 1987-1988 (Box 12)
- Speeches, 1984 (Boxes 12-13)
- Fiscal years 1986-1988 budget material (Box 14)
- Clippings (biographical), 1983-1984 (Box 15)
- Budget status reports, 1985 November (Box 15)
- "Energy and Science (Fall Director's Review Fiscal Year 1989)" briefing binder, 1988-1989 (Box 15)
- Speeches, 1982-1984 (Boxes 16-21)
- Fiscal year 1988 budget material, 1986-1988 (Box 21)
- Gramm-Rudman-Hollings (GRH) Act material, 1985-1987 (Boxes 21-23)
  Includes memos, notes, drafts, and other material related to the Gramm-Rudman-Hollings (GRH) Balanced Budget and Emergency Deficit Control Act of 1985, and the Balanced Budget Emergency Deficit Control Reaffirmation Act of 1987.
  See also: Boxes 5, 135.
- "Task Force on Regulatory Relief" briefing binder, 1987 July (Box 23)
- Writings, 1989 (Boxes 23-24)
  Contains edited drafts of articles, op-ed pieces, book chapters, and reports written by Miller.
  See also: Boxes 40, 51, 66, 116, 142, 151-156, 163.
- Speeches, 1985-1988 (Box 24)
- Fiscal years 1986-1990 budget material (Boxes 24-27)
- Chronological files, 1982-1983 (Boxes 28-31)
  Includes personal and professional correspondence organized by month. Subjects and material relate to both the FTC and the OMB.
  See also: Boxes 45-51, 81-83, 90-91, 107, 109-113, 177.
- Congressional testimony, 1984-1986 (Boxes 31-34)
- Transcripts of Office of Management and Budget (OMB) confirmation hearing, 1985 (Box 34)
- Fiscal year 1988 budget material, 1987-1988 (Box 34)
- OMB appointment material, 1985 (Box 34-35)
  Includes departmental budget briefings, employment statistics, reports, memoranda, and other material for the Director-Designate.
  See also: Boxes 37, 39, 86, 91-92, 106, 128, 134, 136, 138.
- Superconducting semi-collider briefing binder, 1986 (Box 35)
- Fiscal years 1986-1990 budget material, 1985-1990 (Boxes 35-37)
  Includes 1986 "Budget Status Report to the President."
- Clippings (biographical), 1983-1984 (Box 38)
- Fiscal years 1987-1988 budget material, 1985-1988 (Boxes 38-40)
- OMB appointment material, 1985 (Box 39)
- 1988 Republican National Committee subject file (Box 40)
  Includes campaign material and surrogate briefing book.
- Writings, 1985-1988 (Box 40)
- Fiscal year 1988 budget material, 1987-1988 (Box 41)
- Budget proposals by Congress, 1986 (Box 41)
  Contains various proposals submitted to Miller by members of Congress.
- Memoranda and reports, 1986-1988 (Box 41-42)
  Includes file titled "Budget Ideas" with material related to the federal budget, including budget proposals for defense and trade reform.
- Fiscal year 1988 budget material, 1986-1988 (Box 42)
- "Defense Advocacy,", 1986 (Boxes 42-43)
  Includes memoranda, notes, reports, statistics, and briefing material related to the national defense budget.
- Fiscal year 1987-1988 budget material, 1981-1987 (Box 43-44)
- Office of Information and Regulatory Affairs (OIRA) subject file, 1981 (Box 44)
  Includes memoranda and reports.
  See also: Box 57
- Fiscal year 1990 budget material, 1988-1990 (Box 45)
- Chronological files, 1985-1987 (Boxes 45-47)
- Untitled report on small business, undated (Box 47)
- Clippings (biographical), 1986 (Boxes 47-48)
- Chronological files, 1986 (Boxes 48-51)
- Writings, 1972-1981 (Box 51)
- GRH material, 1987 (Box 51)
- Memoranda and reports, 1986-1988 (Box 51)
  Includes file titled "Revenue Options."
- Economic and financial reports, 1986-1988 (Boxes 52-53)
  Contains weekly OMB reports with employment, stock, and budget-related statistics. The reports cover almost every week from February 1986 through September 1988.
- Fiscal year 1989 budget material, 1988-1989 (Boxes 53-54)
- OMB administrative material, 1985-1988 (Box 54)
  Includes 1984 January-June meeting agenda related to the FTC, in addition to travel files reporting OMB business conducted out of office, 1987-1988.
  See also: Boxes 61, 63, 65-66, 71, 124-126.
- OMB appointment material, 1985 (Box 54)
- Printed matter, 1978-1983 (Boxes 55-57)
  Includes various economic journals, along with official FTC and OMB reports.
- OIRA subject file, 1981-1985 (Box 57)
  Includes files titled "Resources I" and "Resources II" with memoranda, notes, reports, and printed matter related to the OIRA.
- Fiscal years 1988-1989 budget material, 1985-1989 (Boxes 58-60)
  Includes file titled "Budget Testimony" with transcripts of congressional testimony and other material related to the 1989 fiscal year budget. Also includes OMB administrative files.
- OMB administrative material, 1985-1988 (Box 61)
  Includes material related to management and day-to-day operations at the OMB.
- "Privitization [sic]" subject file, 1986-1988 (Boxes 61-62)
  Contains memos, reports, and printed matter related to the privatization of industry. Includes two photographs of Reagan with Miller and staff.
- Packard Commission Report subject file, 1986 (Box 63)
- George H.W. Bush subject file, 1986 (Box 63)
  Includes clippings and meeting notes.
- Fiscal years 1988-1989 budget material, 1987-1989 (Box 63)
- OMB administrative material, 1986-1989 (Box 63)
  Includes memos, social invitations, personnel files, and correspondence. Also includes an official profile of Miller titled "Jim's biography."
- "The Reagan Record,", 1982-1988 (Box 64)
  Contains various reports and briefings related to domestic and foreign policy in the Reagan administration, especially the budget deficit.
- FTC reports, 1982-1984 (Box 65)
- OMB administrative material, 1987 (Box 65)
  Includes "Briefing Manual for the Director's Office."
- Fiscal year 1987 budget material, 1982-1987 (Box 65)
- "Writings and Congressional Statements" (collected binder), 1985-1986 (Box 66)
- OMB administrative material, 1986 (Box 66)
- OMB reports and briefing binders, 1987-1989 (Box 66)
  Titles include "Postal Service," "Commission on Executive, Legislative, and Judicial Salaries Report," and "Department of Justice - Review of Major Litigation."
- Fiscal years 1987-1990 budget material, 1986-1990 (Boxes 67-71)
  Includes "Budget Update for President and Cabinet" budget presentation dated July 1987 (Box 67) and State of the Union subject file (Box 68) with notes and memoranda related to potential budget topics in Reagan's 1987 State of the Union Address.
- OMB administrative material, 1985-1988 (Box 71)
  Includes reports, memoranda, and travel itineraries. Also includes "State of the Union" subject file for the 1986 State of the Union Address.
- Fiscal years 1986-1988 budget material, 1985-1988 (Boxes 72-74)
  Includes "Drug Bill/ Executive Order" briefing binder.
- OMB reports and briefing binders, 1985-1986 (Boxes 73-74)
  Titles include: "T-1, T-2, T-3" economic projections, "Overall Budget Advocacy" briefing binder, and "Domestic Advocacy" briefing binder with material related to welfare and economic relief programs.
- Congressional testimony, 1983-1984 (Boxes 75-77)
- OIRA subject files, 1979-1981 (Boxes 77-79)
  Includes memoranda, notes, drafts of written reports, and printed matter related to the OIRA, the President's Task Force on Regulatory Relief, and Reagan's 1981 Executive Order on regulatory relief.
- Teaching file, 1971 (Box 79)
  Contains course syllabi, notes, grades, and lecture materials from an economics course taught by Miller in 1971.
- American Enterprise Institute (AEI) subject file, circa 1980-1981 (Boxes 79-81)
  Contains notes, memoranda, reports, and printed matter related to Miller's tenure with AEI. Also includes a large subject file on "Small Business."
- Southern Economic Association (SEA) subject file, 1981 (Box 81)
  Includes meeting notes, reports, and correspondence related to the Southern Economic Association in 1981.
- Chronological files, 1984 (Boxes 81-83)
- Printed matter, 1981-1988 (Box 84)
  Includes official reports, journals, and telephone directories related to the FTC and the OMB.
- Fiscal year 1989 budget material, 1987-1989 (Box 84)
- "Summary of Litigation Re. Executive Order 12291,", 1985 (Box 84)
- Speeches, 1984 June-July (Box 85)
- Conference papers, 1984 August (Box 85)
  Includes circulated drafts and copies of papers presented at the Hoover Institution Conference on Antitrust Laws and Economic Efficiency in August 1984.
- OIRA issue papers for 1985 Regulatory Program (Box 86)
- OMB appointment material, 1985 (Box 86)
- Hatch Act (revisions) subject file, 1987 (Box 86)
- Printed matter, 1983-1984 (Box 86)
  Contains official FTC reports. Titles include "The First Three Years of the Reagan Administration Leadership" and "Advertising Over-the-Counter Antacids."
- Speeches, 1983-1984 (Boxes 87-89)
- Chronological files, 1981 October - 1982 April (Boxes 90-91)
- OMB appointment material, 1984-1985 (Boxes 91-92)
- Printed matter, 1982-1983 (Box 92)
  Includes "Progress" reports prepared by the FTC, OMB, and the President's Commission on Regulatory Relief.
- Fiscal year 1987 budget material, 1985-1987 (Box 93)
  Includes files related to "CBO (Congressional Budget Office) Estimates," Reagan's 1987 "Economic Bill of Rights" speech, and the federal deficit ("Capital Budget" file).
- FTC material, 1981-1985 (Box 94)
  Includes miscellaneous memoranda, notes, internal reports, and printed matter.
- Fiscal year 1987-1988 budget material, 1986-1988 (Box 95)
- Memoranda, 1981-1985 (Box 95)
- Printed matter, 1978-1985 (Box 95)
  Includes economic reports and publications from AEI and the FTC.
- Fiscal year 1987-1988 budget material, 1986-1988 (Box 96)
- "Tax Reform 1986" subject file, 1985-1986 (Box 96)
  Includes memoranda, notes, internal reports, and printed matter.
- OMB reports and review binders, 1986-1988 (Box 97)
  Titles include "Credit Policy and Management," "Privatization Proposals," "EDGAR Presidential Priority Review System," "Catastrophic Health," and "Reconciliation."
- Fiscal years 1987-1989 budget material (Boxes 97-98)
- Photographs, circa 1985-1989 (Box 99)
  Includes prints of Miller and staff at various events. Also includes three prints of Miller with Reagan at a White House meeting.
- "Department of Defense (DOD) Appeals" subject file, 1985 (Box 99)
  Contains notes, reports, and memoranda.
- Fiscal year 1990 budget material, 1988-1990 (Box 99)
- "Administrative Conference of the U.S. Plenary Session" subject file, 1981 December 10-11 (Box 99)
  Contains agenda, meetings notes, conference proposals, and other related material.
- "Desk" file, 1986-1988 (Boxes 100-105)
  Contains memoranda, correspondence, notes, and printed matter primarily related to the OMB.
- "Housing Bill" subject file, 1987 (Box 102)
  Includes memos, notes, correspondence, reports, and printed matter.
- Memoranda, 1985, 1988 (Box 105)
  Includes file containing "Memoranda to the President."
- Fiscal years 1988-1989 budget material, 1986-1988 (Boxes 105-107)
- OMB appointment material, 1985 (Box 106)
- Chronological files, 1981 (Box 107)
- Speeches, 1981 (Boxes 107-108)
- Chronological files, 1981-1982, 1984-1985 (Boxes 109-113)
- Fiscal years 1987-1988 budget material, 1986-1987 (Boxes 114-115)
- Pete du Pont subject file, 1986 (Box 115)
  Contains newspaper and magazine articles related to du Pont's political career.
- Medicare and Medicaid subject files, circa 1987-1988 (Box 115)
  Includes four files with OMB and Congressional budget estimates related to the expansion of Medicare and Medicaid.
- Fiscal years 1988 and 1990 budget material, 1987-1988 (Box 116)
- Speeches and writings, 1977-1984 (Box 116)
- "OIRA Miscellaneous" subject file, 1977-1981 (Box 116)
  Includes memoranda, correspondence, notes, reports, and news articles.
- Cabinet presentations, 1985-1988 (Box 117)
  Includes budget update reports and cabinet presentations for the 1986-1989 fiscal year budgets.
- Fiscal years 1987-1988 budget material, 1986-1988 (Box 118)
- Correspondence, 1985-1988 (Boxes 118-119)
  Contains letters sent and received by Miller as Director of the OMB. Subjects include "Selected Letters" as well as congratulatory notes related to Miller's nomination and his departure from OMB.
- Fiscal years 1989-1990 budget material, 1987-1989 (Boxes 119-120)
- "SS127 Catastrophic Health" briefing report, 1987-1988 (Box 120)
- Congressional testimony, 1985-1988 (Boxes 120-121)
- "Memoranda to the President,", 1985-1986 (Boxes 121-123)
- Fiscal years 1989-1990 budget material, 1988-1989 (Box 123)
- "Vice President's Task Force on Regulatory Relief" subject file, 1987 (Box 123)
  Includes memos, notes, reports, correspondence, and related printed matter.
- OMB administrative material, 1986-1988 (Box 124)
- Congressional testimony, 1988 (Box 124)
- Miscellaneous subject files, 1985-1988 (Boxes 124-125)
  Includes memos, notes, correspondence, drafts of legislation, economic projections, and news articles related to various Congressional bills and budget-related topics. Titles include "Drug Bill," "Farm Bill (1985)," "Proposition 65," and "Drought." Also includes a file with material related to the 1988 GOP Convention.
- Fiscal year 1989 budget material, 1988-1989 (Box 125)
- OMB administrative material, 1988 (Boxes 125-126)
- Miscellaneous subject files, 1988 (Box 126)
  Titles include "Parental Leave," "Adoption," "Project X" (on Social Security), "Regulatory Relief," and "Privatization" (with material related to a trip to London).
- Fiscal year 1988 budget material, 1987-1988 (Box 126)
- State of the Union Address subject file, 1988 (Box 127)
  Includes memoranda and reports related to budget topics in Reagan's 1988 State of the Union Address.
- Fiscal year 1989 budget material, 1987-1989 (Box 127)
- OMB appointment material, 1985 (Box 128)
- Miscellaneous subject files, 1987-1988 (Box 128)
  Titles include "Corporate Legislation," "Farm Credit Act (1987)," "New Drug Initiative," "Citizens for America," and "White House Talking Points."
- Fiscal years 1987-1990 budget material, 1986-1989 (Boxes 128-129)
- Speeches and Congressional testimony, 1985-1988 (Boxes 129-132)
- National Indicators System (NIS) subject file, 1986 (Box 133)
- Metropolitan Statistical Area, Decatur, Alabama subject file, 1986 (Box 133)
  Includes memoranda, correspondence, notes, reports, and printed matter related to the town of Decatur, Alabama's request to be designated a Metropolitan Statistical Area (MSA).
- Fiscal years 1985-1987 budget material (Box 133)
- OMB appointment material, 1985 (Box 134)
  Also includes an August 1985 "Presentation to the President."
- Fiscal year 1988 budget material, 1987-1988 (Box 135)
- GRH material, 1985-1986 (Box 135)
- OMB appointment material, 1985 (Box 136)
- Miscellaneous subject files, 1985-1986 (Box 136)
  Titles include "New Farm Bill" and "Homeless."
- Fiscal years 1986-1988 budget material, 1985-1988 (Boxes 136-137)
- "Sinners and Saints" event file, circa 1986 (Box 137)
  Includes notes, speeches, joke list, photographs, and other event material.
- OMB budget handbooks, 1988-1989 (Boxes 137-138)
- OMB appointment material, 1978-1985 (Box 138)
  Includes file with "Government Affairs Committee Responses."
- "Quad Commission" subject file, 1986-1988 (Box 138)
  Includes memoranda, reports, and printed matter related to the Quadrennial Commission on Executive, Legislative, and Judicial Salaries.
- Fiscal year 1987-1988 budget material, 1986-1988 (Box 139)
- Republican National Committee (RNC) subject file, 1988 (Box 139)
- General Motors Baltimore Plant subject file, 1973-1980 (Boxes 139-140)
  Includes memos, notes, reports and transcripts of testimony related to a standards case between the Maryland Occupational Safety and Health Services and General Motors, in which Miller served as an expert witness.
- FTC material, 1981-1984 (Boxes 140-142)
  Includes copies of official FTC opinions issued for various cases.
- Writings, circa 1980-1984 (Box 142)
  Includes op-eds, articles, interviews, and official FTC statements written by Miller.
- "Dingell File,", 1981-1982 (Box 143)
  Includes memos, notes, transcripts of testimony, and other material related to the Congressional Oversight Committee led by former Michigan representative John Dingell.
- Writings, circa 1980-1985 (Boxes 143-146)
  Includes journal articles, op-ed pieces, and transcripts of interviews. Box 144 contains a section of files identified as unpublished writings.
- Speeches, 1982-1984 (Boxes 146-148)
- "Fire Hazards" subject file, 1975-1978 (Box 148)
  Contains memos, notes, reports, and printed matter presumably related to an FTC investigation involving fire hazards and flammable materials.
- "Administrative Conference of the United States" subject file, 1981 (Box 149)
  Includes memos, notes, reports, and printed matter.
- Clippings (biographical), 1982-1985 (Boxes 149-151)
- Miscellaneous material, 1978-1982 (Box 151)
  Contains assorted notes, memoranda, and printed matter from 1978-1981. Subjects include federal regulations, FTC testimony, and personnel restructuring within the federal government.
- Writings, 1981-1985, undated (Boxes 151-152)
- "The Performance of the Federal Trade Commission 1977-1984" (report), 1984 September (Box 152)
- Congressional testimony, 1982 (Boxes 152-153)
- Writings, 1982-1984 (Boxes 153-156)
- Speeches, 1981-1985 (Boxes 156-166)
- Congressional testimony, 1979-1985 (Boxes 166-171)
- FTC case opinions, 1981-1983 (Box 172)
  Contains FTC case opinions written or issued by Chairman Miller.
- Event invitations, 1987 (Box 173)
- Fiscal year 1985 budget material (Boxes 173-174)
- Memoranda, 1987 (Box 173)
  Includes Director's memoranda on writing style and writing preferences for OMB staff.
- "Alcohol Advertising Briefing Book,", 1983-1985 (Box 174)
- "ACUS Council Meeting" briefing binder, 1985 April 30 (Box 174)
- Congressional testimony, 1970-1972 (Box 174)
- Clippings (biographical), 1985-1987 (Boxes 175-176)
  Includes memoranda, notes, correspondence, news articles, and reports collectively identified as the "Miller File."
- FTC briefing books, 1983-1985 (Box 176)
  Contains briefing books prepared for the Chairman on "Alcohol Advertising" and "Takeovers."
- Speeches, 1984-1985 (Box 177)
- Chronological files, 1982 (Box 177)
- Economic and financial reports, 1985 (Box 177)
- FTC reports, 1978, 1981 (Box 177)